Alexandria, VA, Lawyers Papers
Alexandria, VA, Lawyers Papers
1786-1865
1786-1834
Special Collections Research Center
2 linear feet (2 document boxes, 1 oversized box)
Formerly the George Deneale Papers. Correspondence and legal papers of three American attorneys from Alexandria, Virginia in the late 17th and early 18th centuries. Papers include warrants, property seizures, and property inventories.
2744146
Biographical History
George Deneale was an attorney in Virginia. He was appointed the Clerk of the Circuit Court of the United States for Alexandria County, a position he held from 1801 until his death in 1818. George Deneale is known to have been acquainted with George Washington and James Madison. He was also a militia officer and a Freemason, and was Grand Master of Alexandria-Washington Lodge, No. 22.
George Gilpin was the first judge of the Orphan's Court of Alexandria in 1800 and became the Postmaster of Alexandria in 1809. George Gilpin was also a member of the same Masonic Lodge as George Washington, and was a pallbearer at Washington's funeral.
Edmund J. Lee was a prominent political and legal figure in Alexandria. He was the Clerk of the Circuit Court of the United States for Alexandria County from 1818 to 1840.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Alexandria, VA, Lawyers Papers contains the papers of attorneys from Alexandria, VA during the late 18th and early 19th century. Three lawyers whose papers are prominently featured in the collection are George Deneale, Edmund Lee, and George Gilpin. The collection is comprised of professional papers, personal papers, and miscellaneous contemporaneous printed items. A few items pertain to Freemasonry in Virginia.
Professional documents contains a variety of legal papers, including a certificate of naturalization, estate documents and inventories, fines from the Mutual Assurance Society against Fire on Buildings of the State of Virginia, property seizures, affidavits, and warrants to the US Marshal service.
Personal papers contain correspondence and other personal documents exclusively of George Deneale.
Printed materials from the mid-19th century include pamphlets and other items.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material within each series is divided into folders by document type (ex: warrants, inventories, etc) and, within each folder, arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Politics, government and public administration; Deneale, George, 1766-1818.; Gilpin, George, 1740-1813.; Lee, Edmund, 1772-1843.; Mutual Assurance Society Against Fire on Buildings of the State of Virginia.; Freemasons. -- Alexandria Lodge, No. 22 (Alexandria, Va.); Freemasons. -- Alexandria-Washington Lodge, No. 22 (Alexandria, Va.); United States. -- Circuit Court (District of Virginia); Lawyers -- Virginia.; Alexandria (Va.) -- History.; Contracts.; Correspondence.; Estate inventories.; Estate records.; Legal documents.; Summonses.; Warrants.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Transfer from Kohen collection, 1963.
Inventory
- Professional documents
  - Contracts signed at Alexandria Court, 1786-1834 (Box 1)
  - Contracts signed at Alexandria Court, 1804 (Oversize 1)
  - Estate documents and inventories, 1794-1824 (Box 1)
  - Estate documents and inventories, 1796-1811; undated (Oversize 1)
  - George Deneale, Clerk indentures, 1797-1800 (Box 1)
  - Legal complaints, 1796-1832; undated (Box 1)
  - Legal papers, 1797-1814 (Box 1)
  - Legal papers, 1801-1827 (Oversize 1)
  - Legal papers, 1820-1855 (Box 1)
  - Mutual Assurance Society Against Fire on Buildings, 1808; court motions (Box 1)
  - Orders to the Marshal of the District of Columbia
    - Arrest warrants, 1790-1812 (Box 1)
    - Arrest warrants, 1812; 1840 (Oversize 1)
    - Arrest warrants, 1815-1840 (Box 1)
    - Court summonses, 1796-1820 (Box 1)
    - Debt collection, 1802-1844 (Box 2)
    - Debt collection, 1804 (Oversize 1)
- Personal papers
  - George Deneale correspondence, 1794-1816 (Box 2)
- Printed materials
  - Miscellaneous, 1882-1884 (Box 2)